<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvord to Lieut. Gen. Cromwel and two vvords for the setling of the King, Parliament and kingdom. / Written by a friend to them, the peace, the ministry, and fundamental laws of the land; and for their restoration and establishment is now publisht to the world, by way of remonstrance.</title>
            <author>Friend to them. the King, Parliament and kingdom.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96924</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862439</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114598</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240946426</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201970</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862439</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862439e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E421[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvord to Lieut. Gen. Cromwel and two vvords for the setling of the King, Parliament and kingdom. / Written by a friend to them, the peace, the ministry, and fundamental laws of the land; and for their restoration and establishment is now publisht to the world, by way of remonstrance.</title>
                  <author>Friend to them. the King, Parliament and kingdom.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, MDCXLVII. [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114598:1"/>
            <p>A WORD TO Lieut. Gen. Cromwel: AND TWO WORDS For the setling of the <hi>King, Parliament and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a Friend to them, the Peace, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, and Fundamental Laws of the Land; and for their Restoration and Establishment is now publisht to the World, by way of REMONSTRANCE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jeremiah 14.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hast thou utterly rejected <hi>Judah?</hi> or hath thy soul loathed <hi>Zion?</hi> why hast thou smitten us, that we cannot be healed? we looked for peace, and there is no good; and for the time of health, and behold trouble.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezekiel 18.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But when the righteous turneth away from his righteousness, <hi>and</hi> committeth iniquity, <hi>and</hi> doth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, shal he live? all his righteousness shal not be mentioned: but in his trespass that he hath trespassed, <hi>and</hi> in his sin that he hath sinned, in them shal he die.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCXLVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114598:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114598:2"/>
            <head>TO His Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> General by the Parliaments Commission.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am sorry I am put upon this unhappy necessity to mind you of your wonted religious and dutiful compliance to the Parliament of England; You have not lost a little in the esteem of godly men; <hi>A word in season,</hi> says <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, is like apples of gold in pictures of silver:</hi> I know very wel, you act not, but you suffer so much, and hand it when they have contrived it, that when God comes to cast out the Counsels of the wicked, and taketh the wise in their own craftiness, you wil hardly escape the danger, being found among the croud; these late carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, managed by Lieut. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his Privy Counsel, do more then intimate a kind of repentance they have made an end of the Wars so soon; or, at least, to give this interpretation upon the former suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses, that it proceedes only from Gods meer mercy to the Kingdom, and not from any sincerity of their indeavors, they ran on, tis true, at first to gain a plause and a name as its very plain by the whole mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Wars, as wel as by these late Treasons, when ever they sent any, not of the right stamp, for this after Rebellion, they ever sent some when the danger was past, of the right faction, to take the honor of the service and success; and so they put all in print one after another, they could confide in, not wanting their Agents in London, even under pension on purpose to blaze their good services up and down the Kingdom, and having the advantage of your Excellencies favor, not seeing this deep layd design was able to cast out, blemish or crush all the orthodox and honest opposers, at least keep them low in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem of the people, and cry up themselves and their Faction as the only instruments God would use, thereby to gain the better advantage and esteem to carry on those desperate Designs of ordering or new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molding the Parliament, which is nothing else but to subvert the Fundamental Laws of the Land, and destroy Religion, which your selves pretended to fight against, for the Parliament; all this while let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114598:3"/> not those successes God has given this Parliament, you have shattered in pieces, and in them to this Kingdom, puff you up: but know, that I know it to be true, that Major Gen. <hi>Skippon</hi> is the Father of that Army, and that most of you usurp the honor of many faithful, valiant Gentl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men of the House of Commons, besides those that you have cast forth of your Army, or could not in conscience stay any longer with you; besides many others that God made instrumental to the giving the Parliament the victory, which, if it be as you say, that they are not Godly, then must you conclude, it is his meer mercy to the Parliament and Kingdom, and not the worth of the Instruments, that is to be looked at in all your successes. Have you not rob'd of their honor, <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Brereton, Rossiter, Brown, Morgan, Massey, Birch, Poyntz, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> and many others? thank God, too many to recount; speak the truth, if any of them have not profest Religion, I am sure none of them have so dishonored Religion, as you have done: and what trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son you are now about, God only knows; but many think you cannot pass without the other purge, to the House of Commons, and to further curb the City? Do you not think that most of the Officers that act now in this design, would have trembled when they were first raised, to have entered into such an Engagement, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to obey the Parliaments Commands, and capitulate with them, and force them to send down Commissioners, to treat with you, as with an Enemy; and have required them to turn out their M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbers, accuse them, and send the Lord Maior <hi>and</hi> Aldermen to pri on: whiles this unparaleld arbitrary power is unrepented, you wil remain under a cloud, and Englands peace <hi>and</hi> truth further indanger'd, as wil appear by this insuing Remonstrance; and could I be any way instrumental to obtain the righting the Freedom of Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, the flourishing of Religion, the setling of Peace, with his Majesties happy concurrence in all his Majesties three Kingdoms, with the sacrifice of my life, I beleeve I should find more comfort in death, then you with all your earthly prosperity, without repentance: Therefore be pleased either to exercise your authority for the vindication of the Parliament, or if you cannot oppose the faction, yet declare your dislike of those apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, that they may not have the countenance of your Commission, which is the only sincere aim and indevor of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The Parliaments truly devoted Servant, the</hi> AƲTHOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114598:3"/>
            <head>A Word to Lieut. General <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his Privy Councel. And two Words for the setling of the King, Parliament and Kingdom.</head>
            <p>WHen by the blessing of God upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and other Forces of the Parliaments, the adverse Forces and Garisons within this Kingdom were dissipated and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and an hopeful way made for the setling of a sound and lasting Peace, on good terms, for the interest of the Kingdom, in stead of the hoped fruit of our labors and hazards, and of the Kingdoms vast expence in the dispencing of Justice and Righteousnes, and the setling and upholding of common Right and Freedom, as if you repented of all your former service; we found immediatly the cross wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of a prevalent party in the Army, who walking under the mask of Saints, and of our only Saviors; and by the advantage of the unsetledness of the Kingdom, and the great pressures and heavy burthens that the Country groans under, took upon you to receive Petitions and become pretenders to be the only sensible men and likely means to relieve the Kingdom; but in truth we fear now, wil prove men of corrupt and private ends and interest, different from, and destructive to the real and common Interest of the Kingdom, even to obstruct and pervert Justice, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure, oppress and crush the peaceable people of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114598:4"/> to abridg and overthrow all just Freedom and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and drive on designs to set up a party and faction of their own in the Parliament, City and Kingdom, by the advantage thereof, to domineer over and inslave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to posterity; and in the pursuance of your designs of setting up your own irreligious or Pharisaical domineering faction to the oppression of all other people and the certain ruin of the Kingdom: you have also had, to further your designs, the great advantage of such pretences as aforesaid, and of all the jealousies among the godly; and whatsoever is amiss in the Kingdom as you have not spared to charge it upon the Parliament; so <hi>Absalon</hi>-like you have playd your parts and called your selves the only Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, the only Saviors, the only sensible, the only able, the only willing men, both to setle Religion and the distempers of the Kingdom; but how you have either setled the King, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the Parliament, relieved <hi>Ireland,</hi> eased <hi>England</hi> of their Taxes, setled Religion, removed Jealousies and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisht Peace, or what hope we have to enjoy them from you, we wil now examine together with the Cal or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that you have to undertake those courses under pretext thereof: For though Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> bear the name, yet its wel known you are the man, you are the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> that moves all in the Army; you are that <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ius</hi> that cries up the magnificence of this great <hi>Diana,</hi> the Army; Gain cloked with a shew of Religion is the very cause of these Divisions; and why your disobedience is so stubbornly defended, committing Idolatry by worshipping this Goddess above all <hi>Asia,</hi> all <hi>England,</hi> even the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to the raising sedition against the Parliament and all the <hi>Pauls</hi> that perswade the people against such vile opinions, and with this silver Smith for to compass the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lver of all earthly prosperity, you run the hazard, if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not the gol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all cele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ial felicity.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114598:4"/>
            <p>Review the Cities Petition and that last from the free born people to the Parliament; you may see by the one into what a labyrinth the Army hath brought the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and by the other, how the City, like a dutiful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, strives to bring it forth again with honor; although indeed the free-born people are in the Right, that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, Grounds and Reasons of the Armies Proceedings, and what presidents they have forced from both Houses of Parliament thereupon, do speak and countenance theirs; but is in truth both alike destructive to the very being of Parliaments, only there is a great deal of difference in power, policy and interest, or else no doubt the Army would take their part, and cal it a providence or foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God has given them, and so take extraordinary courses to make the Parliament and City grant their Petitions. Wel, Gentlemen, let me perswade you to repent, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravel, undo what you have rashly, and in hot blood done, to the dishonor and subverting of the Freedom of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and right the Members thereof, and of this City, for the Kingdoms sake, or else know that deliverance shal come some other way.</p>
            <p>Were it not my duty with righteous <hi>Lot</hi> to be vexed with those unrighteous doings and horrible hypocrisies, and God-loathing juglings; or could I see any other way left to mind you with any hopes of success, of that great account you have to give to the al-seeing God, both for your parts and power; that I have often thought you might certainly be more excusable, if you had hid them in a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin; beleeve it, I would have attempted it and have now been silent; but all other ways have hitherto proved so fruitless, and indeed as to men, seems hopeless, and in the opinion of many godly men, your friends, your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are sounded so much upon machivilian policy, that you must needs lie under great temptations, and run
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114598:5"/> great hazards of making shipwrack of a good conscience, and of the plain truth of <hi>Gods</hi> holy Word, as wel as you do of the good and wholesom Laws of the Land, and of that good old Truth, <hi>The safety of the People is the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Law,</hi> which you so often misapply to your selves, and yet would not allow it to the City, upon your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in a hostile manner, after all the blood and treasure this City hath expended; which indeed is all the visible cause of all that triumph and glorious victories, which you too much attribute to your selves, with such sinful neglect of the good hand of <hi>GOD,</hi> making good that divine complaint, <hi>That you remember not the hand of the Lord, nor the day he delivered you from the enemy; but unworthily sin because his grace hath abounded:</hi> making all these your successes so many arguments, that you are his Saints, and may undertake such courses as are indeed a shame to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that even the wicked are ashamed and blush at; whereas you know, that we can neither know <hi>Gods</hi> love nor hatred by all that is before us; and if those successes were undeniable signs and badges of <hi>Gods</hi> love, yet it remains, that you make it out, how <hi>God</hi> has given you any Cal or Warrant to undertake the medling with the setling of the State and of Religion, which I think unsetling; tossing the King up and down to the danger of his Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, setting periods to Parliaments, taking upon you to protest against the Parliament, and such like: but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with you, where you began your disobedience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> First, Did you not at <hi>Bury, Newmarket,</hi> and elsewhere, without all colour of authority, contrive and set on foot in the Army, and many of them entred into a mischievous and desperate Engagement, besides the first Petition ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the subvertion of the Freedom of Parliament, and of the Liberties of the Nation, to the frustrating of those just and publick ends for which so much blood and treasure
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114598:5"/> hath been spilt and spent in the late Wars to the raising a new War against the Parliament and Kingdom: Did you not summon the City as wel as Court it, only to let you have your wils and sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie your lusts, upon the Parliament, which you cal <hi>Justice indeed against some in the Parliament:</hi> A strange and unheard of Treason, that an Army must be brought up against the Parliament <hi>to force them to deliver up the Members, or do any other thing,</hi> which they would, all the world must needs say, have fain done, if there had been the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st shadow of Justice or Reason, or could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the apparent violation of their Consciences, have suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be done; and what undutiful speeches, what slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and reproaches, and what treasonable attempts you then made upon the Parliament and City, surely you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, by your dayly practices, shal never be forgotten: Be pleased to review the whole Journal of your Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, ever since your first disobedience and traiterous Comment upon the Ordinance of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for disbanding your Army, which though the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament therein exprest it to be their care and duty to this Kingdom, to relieve them from the vast charge of an Army, and for the relieving our distressed brethren in <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet the suffering of both which since, through your disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience too and clamors upon the Parliament are both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, and without Gods great mercy irrecoverable, and how you have changed your principle with your condition let the world judg; that when ever the Parliament came neer to grant your desires, you flew off, either giving some further interpretation of your former, or asking others, whereby the most charitable, that is not an engaged party with you, can hardly think those carriages, as they offer themselvs to our consideration daily multiplying to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with grace and godliness; because I would put you upon the examining your self, give me leave, it is but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114598:6"/> a piece of your own courage, and the same Liberty of Conscience you plead for your selvs; and if the truth of the matter seem to bespeak me not altogether ignorant of your several passages, let them work so much the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon your consciences to a <hi>timely repentance;</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leeve it, without it you may as wel be question<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d here, as it is certain you cannot escape the <hi>searcher of all hearts,</hi> with a thousand Armies, and al your fine words and specious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences in your <hi>long-winded Declarations,</hi> though they may deceive the poor people, having the advantage of a <hi>very distempered and burthened Kingdom,</hi> which the people is not long able to bear. Consider the <hi>Answer of the</hi> 11. <hi>Members to their Charge,</hi> &amp; this great Victory God has lately honored the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> with, for poor bleeding <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with very many other successes given him, all which very much reflects upon the validity of the rest of your <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> against them; for if the L. <hi>Inchiquin</hi> had been <hi>sacrificed</hi> to your fury, or removed from thence, which you make an <hi>Article against the eleven Impeached Members, for defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> in all probability <hi>Ireland</hi> had been helpless and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, for all your <hi>fair pretence,</hi> as far as I can see. And as there is not <hi>any thing</hi> in your <hi>Declarations,</hi> but what makes against you, and wil be without <hi>repentance, a perpetual reproach</hi> unto you as rendring you willing to say anything that wil take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, though never so much out of your sphear and as far from your meaning, &amp; that which could never be effected by an Army. Are not your <hi>pretences</hi> of setling the <hi>King,</hi> &amp; giving the <hi>Country an account of their money</hi> &amp; <hi>easing them of Excise and Tithes, and all other Charges and Taxes, and the rectifying of the several Committees, relieving Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and whatsoever is amiss in the Kingdom?</hi> I say, did you not observe these to be popular and speciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>pretences,</hi> and therefore made use of them to take the people without <hi>any real intentions,</hi> as being things impossible to be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisht
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114598:6"/> by an <hi>Army?</hi> As for what else you lay down as the <hi>ground and reason of your not Dishanding,</hi> that concerns your selves, either as Soldier or Subjects, was it not offred both in point of <hi>indemnity &amp; Liberty of Conscience, with present pay to the Soldiers in the Army,</hi> which being <hi>considered</hi> truly, the Soldiers in conclusion may come to be sensible into what a <hi>loss,</hi> as wel as a <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byrinth,</hi> you have brought them into; so that now there rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins not any thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g to defend your <hi>diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> but what <hi>provocations</hi> you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve since put upon the <hi>Parliament and Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> as the <hi>Ingagement in the City, and the force and violence upon the</hi> 26. of <hi>July</hi> you know wel enough, were but the evil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffects of your <hi>disobedience and ingagement against the Parliament at Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wmarket,</hi> nay of your <hi>besieging the Parliament, and of that bold seisure of his Majesties person</hi> at <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lmby;</hi> all which being considered, it wil appear, the Design of a <hi>New War</hi> is your own, and the <hi>monster</hi> you have bin forming in the bowels of the Kingdom; only it seem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you would take <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> to rather it some where else.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> Now, the next thing to be enquired into is, <hi>year ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to Saint A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hans, and your Summons and Courting the City to give you leave to break the Priviledges of Parliament, or to destroy the very being of it, or both,</hi> which indeed you cal <hi>Justice against some that the Parliament prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts;</hi> truly then we were mad in an absolute trance, stark blind, what with your fair and specious <hi>pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ences,</hi> and by the advantage of your former good service, together with the present di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers of the Kingdom, or else you might wel enough then have come short home; it seemed the <hi>quarrel</hi> was this, <hi>The Parliament was resolved to disband you, and you were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solvd not to disband;</hi> Now you must break the temper of the Hous, or else you could never expect either Justification for what was past, or indeed <hi>impunity or protection</hi> for the time to come, to this <hi>purpose</hi> when the City prest you to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114598:7"/> who they were that you came for Justice against: Is it not true? was it not then tossed up and down amongst you, <hi>how many and who shal we pitch upon?</hi> You through <hi>Gods mercy</hi> having so good choyce of <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in that House that stands fast to the <hi>Interest of England,</hi> and not long after you had agreed to the number, then the men, though not without much grief to you, to leave so many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, fearing you may be put upon another bout, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were so smal: and was it not as true, <hi>that it made you scratch where it did not itch,</hi> to pump for <hi>Articles;</hi> and at last, if you had had no more men then matter, to have back't your <hi>Treason,</hi> you might wel enough have suffered for the <hi>Traitors</hi> your selves.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The next bout to be inquired into is, <hi>your Proposals;</hi> I am not willing to speak to every one, nor indeed to any of them, as not doubting but something may be worthy of consideration; but yet there is not <hi>any thing</hi> worth the free quarter you had while you were making them, nor of the blood and treasure of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that might by <hi>Gods blessing</hi> have been saved had you then obeyed the <hi>Parliament:</hi> and how contemptible you have rendered the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as by many <hi>other w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys,</hi> so by <hi>your Proposals</hi> also, let all men judg in what <hi>danger Religion is in, and the Fundamental Laws of the Land, and the very being of this Common-weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h also:</hi> I say; as all these are shaken by your undervaluing the wisdom of <hi>Parliament</hi> by your making <hi>Proposal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> so do they also render you more inexcusable before <hi>God,</hi> who is the <hi>God of order and not of confusion.</hi> Truly I cannot but think you stop the mouth of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and of such <hi>motions</hi> as you might more truly think from the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> then any of those <hi>delusions of the Devil</hi> you so oft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n cal a <hi>providence,</hi> I mean, its impossible such notorious, perfidious and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Designs,</hi> as you have all along attempted &amp; carried on, ever since <hi>your refusing to disband,</hi> and hath been already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114598:7"/> even the very best of your finest but cheating ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, and your gilded and smooth actions, as you think, but indeed horrid and black in their own nature, and may easily appear in their nakedness and proper colours even to all indifferent men; Are you never upon your pillows, or in any of your <hi>contemplations</hi> put upon no mis-givings; take heed of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hard heart; take heed <hi>God</hi> give you not over to your own lusts, and to beleeve lyes, as if to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy a Kingdom, nay three Kingdoms, and that which far exceeds all, to destroy the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the glory and happiness of this Nation, and indeed of all <hi>Europe,</hi> were to do God good service. I am sure I know the time when <hi>Huson, Oaky, Backster, Grimes, Watson,</hi> and most of the whole Catalogue of the drivers on of these destructive designs to subvert the Freedom of <hi>Parliament,</hi> was so honest and low in their own esteem that they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themselves hardly sit to have waited upon the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament to the House; and I may positively affirm, would not then have intermedled so trayterously to thrust the true Pilots out of doors, and stear the ship of the Common wealth themselves. Wel, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> would it advantage the peace of this Kingdom, I could, what ever you think, implore your repentance with rivers of tears, to see, <hi>O Lord my God,</hi> men, nay professors of Religion thus to break thy Law, and to teach men so to do, nay to punish men that wil not do so, that cannot in conscience and duty to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but make good the <hi>Covenant</hi> to oppose those ungodly doings, that his soul abhors, if it were for nothing else but for these dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings and juglings, seeking all advantages and occasions to draw men into snares, provoking the Parliament and City to defend themselves; and making lyes your refuge, accuse them with whatsoever you know your selves to be guilty of, as a New War; and whatsoever else you made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114598:8"/> Articles of Impeachment against others is truly your own: I am perswaded you would have been much more at a loss, when you were so put to your trumps for Articles, had you not then seen them written in your own carriages; nay you are gone so far, that I am sometimes in hope, as it is in the second Epistle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> Chap. 3. Vers. 9. <hi>That you shal proceed no further; but that your doings and folly shal be made manifest to all men;</hi> By the former Verses of this Chapter, you may see your selves in your colours, and the Lord san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie it unto you, that you may know, in this your day, the things that belong to your peace, before they be hid from your eyes. <hi>This know also, that in the last days perilous times shal come: For men shal be lovers of themselves, cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural affection, truce-breakers, false accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re good; Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasures more then lovers of God; Having a form of godliness, but denying the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; from such turn away. For of this sort are they which creep into houses, and lead captive silly women lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n with sins, led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with divers lusts, Ever learning and never a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le to come to the knowledg of the truth. Now as Jann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hres with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood Moses, so do these also resist the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The next bout is your two thundering <hi>Declarations</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after your <hi>March through the City,</hi> in which you presume <hi>to judg the Parliament to usurp Parliamentary autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> nay <hi>to protest against the Parliament:</hi> And after you had provoked the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>City,</hi> as is before exprest, <hi>to defend themselves from your violence and force,</hi> then you make that an <hi>accusation,</hi> and tel the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of a strange Design to make a <hi>New War:</hi> I beseech you tel me what you find either in the <hi>Law of God</hi> or the <hi>Land,</hi> that may justifie you for those attemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; for, I think, <hi>without some extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114598:8"/> Cal a godly man should not dare to attempt such things as these:</hi> Let me perswade you not to bury in <hi>oblivion</hi> all your former good service, or that which is worse by your apostarizing and degenerating to turn it into <hi>perpetual shame and reproach, not only to your name, but to the profession of Religion:</hi> Consider what advantage all sorts of men now take <hi>to reproach the Parliament and to press destructive things from your late forc'st presidents;</hi> as particularly review the two late <hi>Petitions,</hi> intituled, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he humble Petition of many free born people to the supream Authority of England,</hi> with <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>servations</hi> to one of them, never paraleld before your l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te <hi>courses:</hi> but now, with brazen fac'd impudence, claim what they please and clamor as they please <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainst the Parliament, upon this ground, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it is the Liberty the Army purchased for them and promised to them, and which is but the same thing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effect you have forc'd the Parliament to do for you; remember when the affections were mutual between the Parliament and the City, how plentiful money was, and how terrible was it to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments enemies, and I hope, wil, once again, prove a safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard to Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g and Parliament, when there shal be no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in <hi>England.</hi> But you must think your thus forcing the Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, to Vote and Unvote what you please, makes men to keep their money in their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rses, to let you see the difference between dutiful carriages to a Parliament and undutiful c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges and slanderous accusations both against them and the City; I dare warrant you from ever seeing open purses in this City, until they see the Parliament righted▪ and rheir Members with the Cities restored, that every base fellow may not ask of the Parliament even things against their Conscience and destructive to the Kingdom; and yet upbr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id them, if they deny, with some of your late forc'd presidents for it, even to the non-plusing of our godly Senators, the Freedom and Vindication of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114598:9"/> whom, with his Majesties happy concurrence, I pray <hi>GOD</hi> hasten, that Religion and Peace, the glory and happiness of this Kingdom may be establisht in Peace and Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> And in the next place, particularly to be considered is the many several Letters and other Passages, in order to the aforesaid designs, which by custom, though finely worded, yet indeed speaks more plainly your meaning then former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as your Letter to my Lord Maior and Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel for <hi>money.</hi> Your continuance as an Army and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual pay, I beleeve would prettie wel stop your mouthes from ever attempting the setling the <hi>King</hi> or Kingdom, or releeving <hi>Ireland,</hi> or taking any of the Taxes from off the the poor Country, without it be to take off threescore thousand pound a moneth, and put one hundred upon the Kingdom in liew thereof; but as it is an unparaleld affront to the City, medling with that you have no colour of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for, so can you not expect they should lend or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burse any money for your use, or do you the least favor, more then pray for your <hi>Repentance,</hi> being every day so ill requited for their old matchless favors to your Army, though it seems by you now forgotten, or very ungrateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembred: If there be any Arrears due, upon any <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> from particular men, who have so laid out themselves in their zeal for the Kingdoms good, that they now want it to buy bread; though you so ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully requite them. Whats this to the <hi>Representative</hi> body of the City? from whom you cannot in Reason expect they should lend you one groat, before you return to your <hi>obedience,</hi> and right the Members of both Houses, and of this City, you have so maliciously and falsly accused in your <hi>several Declarations.</hi> And stil when the <hi>Parliament</hi> is upon any Debate, and resolves upon any Particulars in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Peace and Setlement of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> you set upon some debate in your <hi>Junto</hi> or mock-Parliament, I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114598:9"/> mean, the General Councel of the Army, to stop it; saying, it is against your ingagement or proceedings, and indeed I think so it is; as this last weeks <hi>Diurnal</hi> says you say of the Votes for disbanding the supernumerary Forces of the Kingdom; but the world sees how you use the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, City and Kingdom, nay the three Kingdoms in them; and how fain you would, nay you wil have a New War, without they wil part with their Religion, their Liberty, and a free Parliament, to have one made up of Mechanicks, and such of their servants as are in the Army, now indeed their masters; continual threatning of the Parliament, and your late threatning the City for spending money whilest you take free-quarter, meat and drink, on the Country, all set you out pretty wel, that a man may almost conclude beforehand, what your next attempt must be, in order to your design, if they be but diligent obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and compare your past proceedings with the present face of things: Dare you promise never to force the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament more, or while you shoot others to death for your offences, to stil the noise, wil you not compleat the Levellers begun treasons, and turn out the other parcel of Members your selves, and destroy the Government of this famous City? and to say no worse, make King, Parliament and City all your slaves at a clap; they say you threaten a sudden storm, if M. <hi>Peters</hi> prove not a false <hi>Prophet:</hi> If you talk of Monopolizing, this is a Monopoly with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, to Monopolize the Religion, Liberty and property of <hi>England and Ireland,</hi> all under the devotion of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, at once; no doubt if you can get your pattent sealed, though with blood, you wil, having left a blank, put in <hi>Scotland</hi> afterwards.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O England, dost thou yet want eyes to see,</l>
               <l>What gallant Saints are digging graves for thee;</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114598:10"/>
               <l>And canst thou stil give credit to these elves,</l>
               <l>Who steal thy wealth, for to make fat themselves!</l>
               <l>These Hypocrites, though cloth'd with holy zeal,</l>
               <l>Are thy obnoxious fates, destroy thy Weal.</l>
               <l>They are meer outsides, have an holy tone,</l>
               <l>Yet are but devils masked, every one.</l>
               <l>Their actions tend to Murder, Lust and Pride,</l>
               <l>Sacriledg, Treason, and all ills beside.</l>
               <l>For shame then sit not stil, until you be</l>
               <l>Past hope, recovering this Conspiracie.</l>
               <l>They drive amain, til all about is hurld,</l>
               <l>And their base fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y fire our English World.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> But in the last place, as I find not any thing you have said to have the least shadow of reason, or matter, to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any of your proceedings; which if they were granted, yet is there so much jugling, hypocrisie and fraud through the whole Journal of your proceedings, that they favor not at all of godliness, nor of a true <hi>Nathaniel, in whom there is no guile,</hi> it were worth the while for <hi>Lieu: General Cromwel</hi> to examine himself, and say, <hi>whats the matter with me that was once the object of all your love, in all your prayers and praises, but now thus under a cloud:</hi> The truth is, to deal candidly with you, you have walked in the clouds, ever since those unhappy backslidings of yours, if all sorts of men be not mistaken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> First, His Majesties late partakers, as you cal them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom you have fought all these Wars, sometimes take you for a new man, but make the old reckoning, to <hi>love the Treason but hate the Traitor;</hi> sometimes they take you for a Jugler, or one of <hi>Peters</hi> Hocus-pocus Comrades, or at best a politick Enemy that hath self ends in all your pretences; that unless you can establish the King so, that you may be establisht in the head of an Armie, thereby to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114598:10"/> have your designs establisht by Act of <hi>Parliament;</hi> its thought You resolve to venter a brush yet with both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Lieut. Colonel <hi>Lilburn,</hi> with the rest of the free-born people, you may take the Levellers among the croud, doth charge you with much dissembling and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie, a sin that but indifferent Protestants abominate; if you review their Papers upon mature deliberation, there is hardly any treason or mischief ever attempted by them, but they say they received incouragement to have your countenance and concurrence; but it may be, you wil say, so they shal; when their designs are ripe, but its not time yet for me to appear.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, The honestest Independents do conclude you are now under a temptation, and do think that you have taken too much Liberty of Conscience to shuffle and cut; I was informed that Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerig</hi> much doubted, how your carriages in things, he then instanced in to you, could stand with grace and godliness, when he told you, <hi>If you proved not an honest man, he would never trust a fellow with a great nose again, for your sake;</hi> its very like him, he is very down-right usually according to his principles.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> Fourthly, The Presbyterians they stand amazed, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in private, spending whole days in prayer, that God would give you grace, and that the Gospel might not be dishonored and wounded through your sides; if you would but take notice, you may see a general palefac'dnes through the Kingdom in some for the dearness of bread, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for the great cause of fear there wil be a famine of the Word of God, the great contempt and scorn of the Ministers and Ministry; countenancing a few dissenting brethren, nay abundance of dissolute and Jesuitical prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled persons to affront the godly Ministry and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Jesus Christ, to the apparent breach of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114598:11"/>
               <hi>Covenant</hi> you made with the high God in that point, not opposing Heresies and Schisms, but if you speak as long as you live, you can never wipe away that palpable breach of the Covenant, that not only suffered the priviledges of <hi>Parliament</hi> to be broken; but have broken them your selvs so impudently and notoriously, that Heathens wil condemn you and reproach Religion: There is two remarkable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods wrath against Covenant-breakers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spisers; the one Divine, the other Humane; both worth your Observation: as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Joshua <hi>having made a</hi> League <hi>and</hi> Covenant <hi>with the</hi> Gibeonites, (<hi>notwithstanding they had craftily circumvented and deceived</hi> Joshua <hi>therein) which remained inviolable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of</hi> Israel, <hi>til the days of King</hi> Saul, <hi>who, in his Zeal, had (it seems) slain some of the</hi> Gibeonites, <hi>and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devored to have destroyed them all from among the</hi> Israelites: <hi>Hereupon the wrath of the Lord was greatly incensed against</hi> Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>which brake not out til King</hi> Davids <hi>days, who was sorely vexed with a fearful Famine over the whole Land, for at least three years together incessantly; which so greatly grieved and troubled</hi> David, <hi>that he enquired of the Lord what might be the cause thereof; And the Lord answered him, that it was for</hi> Sauls <hi>sake, and for his</hi> bloody-house, <hi>because he had broken the</hi> Covenant, <hi>and slain the</hi> Gibeonites, <hi>and his wrath would not be appeased, til holy</hi> David, <hi>in just revenge of this breach of</hi> Covenant, <hi>had delivered up unto the</hi> Gibeonites <hi>(as they, by Gods wil, had demanded)</hi> 7 <hi>of</hi> Sauls <hi>Sons, or nearest Kindred to be hanged by them, as they were, and then (and not til then) was God pacified, and the Famine immediatly ceased.</hi> Iosh. 9. <hi>and</hi> 2 Sam. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uladislaus <hi>King of</hi> Hungary, <hi>and</hi> Amurath <hi>the great</hi> Emperor <hi>of</hi> Turky, <hi>after fierce wars between them, having concluded a happy and honorable peace for the said King of</hi> Hungary, <hi>and they having entred into solemn</hi> League <hi>and</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114598:11"/> Truce, <hi>by interchangeable writings, sealed and delivered each to other; not long after,</hi> Julian, <hi>a</hi> Cardinal <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>having perswaded him to renounce and violate this</hi> Covenant <hi>and</hi> Peace; <hi>the King of</hi> Hungary <hi>secretly prepared mighty forces suddenly to invade and set upon the</hi> Turks <hi>Territories, and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murath <hi>the great</hi> Turk, <hi>at last hearing of this unexpected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion by</hi> Uladislaus, <hi>made mighty preparation, presently, to oppose him; entred into a pitcht field against him, in brief,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murath, <hi>observing a mighty slaughter of his men, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and his whole Army in great danger to be discomfitted, and beholding also in the</hi> Hungarian-<hi>displayed-banners, the picture of a</hi> Crucifix, <hi>he presently pluckt forth the</hi> Writing <hi>out of his bosom, wherein the late</hi> League <hi>or</hi> Covenant <hi>was comprised, and holding it up in his hand, with his eyes cast up to heaven, he said these words.</hi> Behold, thou crucified Christ, this is the League thy Christians, in thy name, made with me, which they have without cause violated. Now if thou be a God, as they say thou art, revenge the wrong now done unto thy name, and unto me, and shew thy power upon thy pernicious people, who in their deeds deny thee their God, <hi>presently after this, the fight was fiercely followed on both sides, but it pleased the Lord, that</hi> Uladislaus <hi>was put to the worst, and in the fight, slain by one of the</hi> Turks Janizaries, <hi>and his head cut off, and presented to</hi> Amurath, <hi>in the midst of the battel, who commanded it to be set upon the top of a Lance, and carried up and down in the field, to the terror of the</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, <hi>who presently fled and left</hi> Amurath, <hi>total Victor, with a most mighty and lamentable slaughter of the</hi> Christians. <hi>From both which most pregnant and eminent examples, we may profitably make this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent use and application. That if the Lord God hath so tender a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to the exact performance of</hi> Leagues <hi>and</hi> Covenants, <hi>made not only 'twixt</hi> Man <hi>and</hi> Man, Christian <hi>and</hi> Christian, <hi>but even between</hi> Christians <hi>and</hi> Turks, <hi>or</hi> Infidels (<hi>such as the</hi> Gibeonites <hi>and this</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murath <hi>were) O how much more tenderly affected,</hi> and <hi>severely exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated, wil he be for the breach of</hi> Covenants, <hi>made betwixt</hi> his own glorious Holiness, <hi>who is a</hi> Consuming fire, <hi>and</hi> Wormling-Man, <hi>who is but as</hi> Combustible Stubble <hi>in his presence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114598:12"/>
            <p>But now you wil say, we have not broken the <hi>Covenant,</hi> nor done any of these things you suppose we have; and if you review our Declarations, you wil see we stand for the <hi>Freedom of Parliament, the setling of the King, the relieving of Ireland, the taking away of all Taxes, the giving a good Account of the Countreis money, the rectifying the Committees, and the mending whatsoever is amiss, defending the City, and endevoring a right understanding with the Scots, the hindering of a New War, the dispencing of Justice and Righteousness equally unto all the Nation, to this purpose was our advance to London, to setle the Speakers in a free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Indeed your Declarations are ful fraught with many fair and specious pretences, and not without some notorious contradictions, and are in truth all, from first to last, excepting what they exceed, the very lively relation of the acting of <hi>Absaloms</hi> Treason over again; if you read the story and your own Declarations and practices, you wil find them all along run paralel: But in particular, all your pretences cannot so blind the world, but they wil very wel remember that the Parliament was a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> before you medled with them; indeed had it been your good fortune to have changed Treasons with that Rabble Rout on the 26. of <hi>July;</hi> or could you, with all your wit, have procured such a bout before your Petition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, or your refusing to disband and advance to St. <hi>Abbans,</hi> you might, for ought I know, have cozened the wisest, and have ruined, with a great deal of applause, the most innocent in all the House of Commons; and in stead of eleven you might have dozend them up in faggots for the fire of your fury. But you must not think we shal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be in a trance, fears and dangers continuing long the sting wil vanish, and we grow better acquainted with you and your designs, then always for sober men, men that are come to themselves, to think the turning out of the 11.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114598:12"/> Members, by the power and force of an Army, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary courses, is the way to make a <hi>Free Parliament;</hi> indeed, I think, its the way to make a <hi>Free Parliament House,</hi> if they be forcst to leave it to avoyd your fury: I remember the good ordinary old way of having a Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, was, <hi>That not any should take notice without, what was done within the walls of that House:</hi> You must have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Cal for this your extraordinary Course; or it must be extraordinary mercy that must pardon your extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary sin; for upon that score stands all other of the mischieves you pretend to remove, and indeed are really the fruit and evil effects of your disobedience, which you very wel know would all vanish, if the cause, your diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience were removed; which makes godly men wonder you dare thus dissemble to pretend the removing of those miseries, you do, nay you must, as long as you are an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, continually multiply. What has occasioned all the Taxes upon the Kingdom, but their Armies? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no it has ever been abated since you have taken upon you the Government of the Kingdom, or ever is like to be, as long as you continue, I wil leave it to all rational men to judg. Besides, what wil become of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the known Laws of the Land, of the Subjects Liberty and property; what of our Religion? I think we shal enjoy as much as the Martyrs did, <hi>either to turn or burn.</hi> Do you think the Kingdom is so foolish to beleeve an Army can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver setle a happy Peace, while you undertake these unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful course? Certainly you are mad, I doubt you make ill application of the footsteps of Gods providence towards you, in the several successes he gave you in these late Wars. Are you not grown drunk with pride, passion, and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; attributing to your selves Gods only precious ones, as I have heard some say, they now live above means, and therefore now conclude, that because your designs have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114598:13"/> so wel prospered; that its the meer providence of God, and by and by fancy some divine revelation, as some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Cal hereunto, or, with M. <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> that Dooms day is past; as indeed it were wel for such practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as yours, that it were; but its truly rather some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilish temptation, taking the advantage of this opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to wit, the sword in your hand, together with the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of mans nature, to be medling with forbidden fruit, strives to draw you under that Curse in <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>that though you hear the word of the Curse, yet you shal bless your selves in your wickedness, and say you shal have peace and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, though you walk in the stubbornness of your own hearts.</hi> How many times hath the House of Commons given an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to Petitioners, That it is the duty of the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>acquiesce</hi> in the Wisdom and Justice of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and especially very lately; since your non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, as you cal it, but indeed really preferring your own before theirs, inviting the people to Petition you for Justice; and seeing you have thus inthralled the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the City, to salve it as wel as may be, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting too much dishonor or seeming guiltiness, by own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your faults, to recover the Parliaments honor, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed given way to your Agents to scrue in words in their late Petition, that might out of the least sence of duty you ow to the Parliament, move you to meet them with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of Love and tears of Repentance, if you prove not Principle-shaken as wel as Planet-shaken; for God knows and your own consciences tels you, all those dishonors, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, treasons and force, put upon the Parliament, are from and followed your disobedience and first ingagement. I heard the Reformadoes say, they took examples from you; but if you can play the Machivilian to draw in the City to betray their own innocency, and lay your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons upon their own shoulders: I wil say, if <hi>Achitophel</hi> or <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salom</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:114598:13"/> were now alive, they were but fools to <hi>Oliver Cromwel.</hi> They say Lieut. Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> wil discover the time, place and design you have been driving on, all this while: And thus much I can tel you, if he does not, others wil, that is more privy to your designs then you think of, when its seasonable, without your <hi>repentance,</hi> which you have good reason to hasten, considering the blow God hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which doth exceedingly discover your <hi>Articles</hi> to be meerly maliciously invented from the pride of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt, that you could not rule all in the House as wel as in the Army; your notorious false asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions you cast upon that incomparable gallant and godly Christian Soldier Major General <hi>Skippon,</hi> to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, as much as you can, the total giving up of <hi>Ireland</hi> to the Rebels merciless hands, and the utter destroying of all our <hi>English</hi> Forces there; for, you must think, none wil contribute to <hi>Ireland,</hi> as long as they see, if ever you send any, its like to destroy those we have already there, and losing what we have gained, to send such as are of your own Faction to affront my Lord <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> as he hath already declared, and play such pranks as you do in <hi>England,</hi> to the destruction of all together. What hath been said to any of your pretences is sufficient to say to all; they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually without the precinct of your power to perform; and then in point of Hypocrisie, jugling, defraud, dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, sins, far from Saints, you must needs be guilty in also, save only the relief of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that I confess you have forc'd within your power to perform, and made very large promises to the Kingdom upon it; but considering the opportunities and advantages you have had, together with all your dealings with the Parliament and Kingdom, and your staying and breaking the neck of that Army they had prepared to send thither, under the notion, <hi>that it was a design to break your Army;</hi> I say, as we may guess by that,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114598:14"/> what performances we might expect in the rest, were they in your power; so truly we may fear the blood of <hi>Ireland</hi> wil stand upon your score; surely it was a much better design, if any, to break your Army, then your design of hindering <hi>Irelands</hi> relief, to keep an Army upon free quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>England,</hi> only to establish your selves and your party <hi>to domineer over and inslave the Kingdom to posterity;</hi> But you must needs be guilty also of the <hi>sin of Hypocrisie, when you ingaged your self the Army should disband at the Houses Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and when you wisht you and your sons lives might be the sacrifice to appease the Mutiny and discontents of the Soldiers;</hi> when since it appears, by your practices, you had a deep hand in it your self, especially by your late <hi>compliance</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with the <hi>former Agents</hi> and <hi>your mul iplied Treason</hi> you have since builded upon that <hi>foundation,</hi> to the astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the godly, to see you thus sin against <hi>your knowledg,</hi> to the wounding of <hi>your conscience,</hi> that cannot but know, <hi>That obedience had been much better then sacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of Rams.</hi> And whereas it is <hi>apparent,</hi> by all that has been said, and many <hi>other evidences,</hi> too many to recount, yet there being some <hi>Treasons</hi> crept in among the <hi>Croud,</hi> which neither the <hi>People,</hi> nor <hi>your Soldiers,</hi> nor <hi>your selves</hi> either sees not or thinks them not much, for <hi>your credit,</hi> to be seen, <hi>you</hi> strive so much to thrust them in, in the dark; Therefore I shal instance in some more, besides <hi>Your Engagement and force done upon the Parliament,</hi> much unlike the <hi>Rule our Savior</hi> hath given you, as all those strange <hi>expressions and extraordinary courses,</hi> as You cal them; and I am sure without anie Cal from God, or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the Law of the <hi>Land,</hi> to make the <hi>Parliament</hi> recal their <hi>Declaration</hi> against you, and then lay the blame thereof upon themselves; mark how you dance up and down in glistering <hi>words,</hi> though with much swelling <hi>pride,</hi> impudently requiring them to <hi>Unvote their Votes,</hi> that cal'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114598:14"/> any from the <hi>Armies Rebellion;</hi> then they must Vote, <hi>that You are their Army;</hi> then they must Vote you <hi>present Pay, equal with them that, in obedience to the Parliament, left your Army.</hi> What <hi>horrible dishonor</hi> do you force upon the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> and surely <hi>wound your own consciences,</hi> if they be but half so <hi>tender</hi> as you <hi>pretend:</hi> And were your cause just and Gods cause, yet I am sure <hi>Gods children</hi> had never <hi>any Commission</hi> from him to use any <hi>indirect means</hi> to bring it to pass, or <hi>carry on</hi> his work <hi>in their hands,</hi> as hath been shewed you have done all along in your proceedings; and exercise such insolency over the <hi>Parliament</hi> as was never pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raleld before, but by a foolish Proverb, among the sharp Country Dames, <hi>That if they say the Crow is white, they wil make their maids say so too;</hi> they used that to shew their authority over their <hi>servants,</hi> but I never met with any that exercised so much insolency over their <hi>masters,</hi> before your <hi>Papers and Practices;</hi> besides, your very foundation is lavd upon lyes and falshoods, as particularly in the <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> to your Threatnings, you lay down as the ground, to justifie the Result of that <hi>Declaration,</hi> to be this, <hi>That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the pretended House of Commons, with four or five Lords of the same model for an House of Peers, they presume to proceed to act as a Parliament:</hi> I need not tel you of the falshood of this pretence, because, I hope, by this time, all men sees it; for all the world may know, there is but part of this model in question, though my Lord of <hi>Pembroke</hi> escaped but nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly; and yet there is seven Lords now under the <hi>Black-Rod</hi> of the same model. Is not this a lye think you?</p>
            <p>But to draw all to a <hi>Conclusion;</hi> it may be, you wil say, <hi>the world may see your good intentions, by the good service you did at the late Randezvouz of the Army, in quelling and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting the Levellers;</hi> truly thats one of your smallest pieces of Machivilian policy, when you, like a skilful Physitian or rather a subtil Mountebank, have deadly wounded a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114598:15"/> Kingdom, should now and then give it some ease and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshment, especially to lay by such blades that were too plain dealers for your turn; and it made much for your own profit and self-ends, no doubt, you hoping thereby to gain applause, and yet cal it a <hi>providence;</hi> if you can ever see a better opportunity for so good an exchange, as to get your designs countenanced by Parliamentary authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This has been your only sin, that in all the Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, since this unhappy difference, you have playd the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terman, <hi>look one way and row<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> another;</hi> or, at least, speak <hi>Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>son,</hi> in such ambiguous terms, that if it take not, like the new <hi>Vice-Admiral,</hi> you can either make a Recantation or desire Liberty of <hi>Conscience</hi> to give it another interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; so that it is not all your Speeches in the House of Commons, but <hi>Repentance,</hi> that must bury in Oblivion your late miscarriages; for if you say you have performed what you promised, then wil the Kings unsetlement, the Parliaments Renting, <hi>Englands</hi> Taxes, <hi>Irelands</hi> misery, the Cities Trading, the palefacedness of the poor, the cries of the Country against free quarter, the increase of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, the mourning of the Godly, the despising of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and Ministry, the contempt of the Parliament; all witness against you; and do as wel proclaim to the world your hypocrisies as your treasons; as its treason for you to attempt the doing of them, so you then also wel knew, if your designs took effect, you must establish Peace and Free-quarter both together, or at least all other burthens that lie upon the Kingdom at this day, with [I may posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm) the increase and not the decrease of any of our fears either of a New War, Discontents, Divisions, Taxes, or any other mischievous design, either against the Gospel or Civil Government; for, to be sure, whatever is not establisht by the King and a Free <hi>Parliament,</hi> wil not be lasting to this Kingdom, which you wofully and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114598:15"/>
               <hi>in the whole Journal of your proceedings,</hi> endevor to subvert and overthrow. Was not the <hi>Parliament</hi> as free, when they Voted <hi>your Disbanding,</hi> as they were when they gave Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his <hi>Commission,</hi> and establisht the New Model? Do not you infinitely betray your own cause you have fought in? Did ever any but his Majesty, and those that defend his Cause, ever thus question the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor his Majesty, since your Army was raised; and now, upon the close, is pleased to recal his <hi>Proclamations and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations;</hi> and yet you, as if you resolved to make them <hi>contemptible,</hi> and render invalid all they have done, even to the betraying of your own selves, and telling the world, <hi>You either know not, or care not, what you fight for, or whether you have any authority or no, more then some bare fancy of a cal from the Spirit,</hi> but indeed wil rather prove some delusion of the devil, that your good meaning wil bear you out; surely I think either it must be granted by the free people of <hi>England, That the freedom of Parliament consists in the major part of the Members,</hi> or else it must <hi>needs bring all to confusion, and overthrow the Fundamental Laws of the Land;</hi> and if you grant that, I am sure you can never justifie that Act <hi>of forcing the major part either to forbear their coming to the House, or to submit themselves to the Judgment of the minor;</hi> All which you did require in that <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> of the eighteenth of <hi>August;</hi> which I know you would fain have <hi>obtained</hi> more closely, and with less noise in the Kingdom, if all your policy and party in the House could have effected it; but you knowing your whole courses so <hi>destructive, not only to the Freedom, but even to the very being of Parliaments;</hi> and your selves in such a <hi>tottering and dangerous condition,</hi> not only in danger to lose your design, but even to receive your <hi>just Rewards,</hi> resolved to adde drunkennesse to thirst, and to make the <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> the OFFENDERS.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114598:16"/> And when you had made way with your swords, through those difficulties you have met with, and saw a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral calm through the Kingdom, then Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in his Colours; and tells you his judgment was, that you might well enough, as farr as he saw, leave juggling, or taking so much pains to study for fine phrases, or glistering pretences, to colour over your black designs, or for any more Articles of Impeachment; and without any more ado, take all that are not of your party and confederacy, as men not for common Right and Freedom, or for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of <hi>England,</hi> and turn them out of the House by head and shoulders. What think you did M. <hi>Peters</hi> mean else in his last Pamphlet by these words, <hi>That he could wish the people might now know what they must trust to, and trust God with the management of it;</hi> It seems by this, your designs have been such, as you dare not trust God with, all this while. Well, I tremble to read over all your Papers, to see how impudently, all along, you appropriate the present sword in your hand, the victory and successes, you have hitherto had, in any of your sinful and treasonable attempts, upon the Parliament, City and Kingdom, to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations God hath given you; and therefore wil now take such extraordinary courses, to make the Parliament satisfie you, by Thursday next as God shal direct you: when you persued your resolutions, we saw no directions from God, in print, for your warrant, and I beleeve Repentance wil be your best plea, when you come to give an account to the Almighty for that treasonablebout; Is not this, think you, to bless your selves in your hearts, saying, <hi>you shal have peace against the word of his Curse;</hi> for I think that Gods curse wil follow the extraordinary course without your extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Repentance; and then you say, in the front of one of your Declarations, That by the manifold dispensations of Gods Providence, the Army was led to advance against
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114598:16"/> the Parliament and this City; you may remember that would not serve the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> turn, for but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to bring up the Northern Army against the Parliament: Truly it were wel worth the while for you to Review the <hi>Parliaments first Remonstrance,</hi> and the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment</hi> of the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the BP. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and whatsoever else was the ground and reason of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments making War, and compare them with your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Practices, and you wil see only this difference, that you have a better art to cover them with the cloak of Religion, and also the very trick of making the people beleeve <hi>God is of your Confederacy;</hi> and for you that ingaged in this quarrel, and hath done a great part of this work, to act the self-same things your selves, in the face of the Son of God, what a shame is this to the Gospel? <hi>how wil the Heathens triumph and wicked men rejoyce?</hi> I cannot, without tears, set pen to paper, but break forth and say with <hi>David, Wo is me that I am constrained to dwel in Mesech and to have an habitation in the tents of Kedar.</hi> What remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but that you presently examine your own selves, and not any longer thus sinfully make application of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Sword, to be by <hi>God</hi> given you for any of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid ends: true it is, <hi>God</hi> suffers it to be in you hands, for our sins <hi>God</hi> may justly scourge us by you, and for other ends best known to himself; but for you to cal it the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>God</hi> has given you, to alter and change the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of Church and State; thus boldly to teach, check and balance the power of Parliament, to force them to do and undo what you please, to appoint periods to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and give rules and directions for the succession of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to take such extraordinary courses as you think fit, to make the minor part of the Members punish the major, and to require reasons why such and such Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers give their consents to Votes, and to araign, adjudg and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114598:17"/> condemn Members in <hi>your Papers</hi> for things done in the House, with a thousand other particulars, either before mentioned or may be read in your <hi>printed papers and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices;</hi> which if the whole Catalogue were naked before the whole <hi>Army,</hi> I <hi>presume</hi> to be <hi>confident</hi> they would blush to see how they have been meerly abused and drawn in by the craft and subtilty of many of you, even with a great deal of <hi>detestation and hatred,</hi> &amp; even <hi>brand upon</hi> them that black badg of the Gunpowder <hi>traitors,</hi> as their <hi>Just Livery,</hi> whose <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and whose <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>Faction.</hi> Nay I am <hi>confident</hi> your <hi>ingenuity</hi> was such, that if all the <hi>undutiful expressions, and all the breaches of Parliament priviledges, and all the mischieves,</hi> though very neatly drest in the <hi>gaudy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel</hi> of <hi>your dainty fine wits,</hi> should have been <hi>presented</hi> to you, at once, in any of your <hi>General Councels,</hi> you would have said, <hi>What am I a dog that I should do these things?</hi> and, at least, have <hi>served him, as you served</hi> Joyce <hi>for ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of their Soveraign;</hi> or as you did with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>White</hi> for offering his <hi>opinion,</hi> which you justifie in your practice, <hi>that there is no Law but the Sword;</hi> and have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced it at least for the present, as being more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to own it, before men, then commit it before God, although you punished him with the loss of his <hi>Cornets</hi> place, to be a <hi>Captain,</hi> or from a <hi>Captain</hi> to be a <hi>Major:</hi> But indeed if you wil but see that your selves, that others see, <hi>as clear as the Sun at noon day,</hi> you may see, that all <hi>your Papers and Carriages,</hi> from first to last, are <hi>nothing</hi> but an <hi>Arraignment</hi> of the whole <hi>proceedings</hi> of the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> and a <hi>Commending of the Wisdom and Justice of your General Councel of the Army before them; traiterously indevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to raise up an universal disesteem among the people, to this Parliament;</hi> and if you could but live without <hi>Pay, and yet pay your quarters,</hi> peradventure you might always rule the Rost, and the <hi>Kingdom be so content.</hi> But, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114598:17"/>
               <hi>Kingdom,</hi> by this time, sees, its impossible for you to do them any good but by being <hi>obedient to your masters;</hi> your <hi>disobedience</hi> hath cost <hi>England, Ireland and Scotland,</hi> as much treasure, besides what blood, God only knows, by <hi>your hindering</hi> Major General <hi>Skippon,</hi> and gallant <hi>Masseys</hi> Army from going; I say, its thought it hath lost them as much as would have payd your whole <hi>Army,</hi> and have eas'd the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and have welnigh recovered its <hi>wonted happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> at worst have freed us from those fears we now he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and you <hi>continually increase</hi> with some <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Design</hi> of Your own, or <hi>crying up</hi> one plot or other, to give the <hi>better advantage</hi> to Yours: Whereas a man may read all the <hi>ground and reason of your contest</hi> only to be, with <hi>Haman,</hi> to get the Victorie over all the <hi>Mordecays</hi> in the House, by the <hi>advantage</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> and the service that hath been done by them, cozening the <hi>Soldiers,</hi> under the <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tence of standing for thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pay and other benefits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or them,</hi> while You only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im at Your self-interest, to their extream prejudice and undoing, who would be glad of their <hi>Pay</hi> as it was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them; which they were made beleeve, never was. And they being also to be sharers of this <hi>designed slavery and common calamity,</hi> when You have served Your own turn of them, by committing this <hi>horrid design,</hi> which all the world sees clearly now is to establish your own greatness and the affected <hi>domination</hi> of Your selves and Your partie over all others; and in truth is, what ever You <hi>pretend,</hi> the prejudice, trouble and suppression of all, that appear for the <hi>truth and power of Religion,</hi> or <hi>for the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdom, to the advancing, at once, both of Civil and Ecclesiastical Tyranny upon all these considerations:</hi> I say laying aside what ever your wits may afford you to carp at, either in respect of the plainness of the stile or any thing else, although, I may in prudence desire to be concealed whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I see you, through Gods mercy, in a more godly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114598:18"/> temper, so, I thank God, the truth of the matter and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of my aim would carry me, with more comfort, through the fire of your fury, then I could have in being silent, though a man indeed may better write against the <hi>Father, Son and Holy Ghost,</hi> then such Scripture Truths as meet with your own impieties in these days; but for <hi>Sion</hi> sake I cannot hold my peace; and, according to your own principles, I may take a piece of your courage to write as wel as you; Therefore I beseech you, for the Gospel sake, for the Peace of <hi>England, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotlands</hi> sake, for your own souls sakes, return to your obedience, <hi>Arise and waken your selves, and seek the Lord, while he may be found, cal upon him, while he is neer;</hi> while you were obedient, God honored you with many Victories, honor you God now, in the close, with this glorious Conquest, even over your own hearts, to the subduing of all your lusts, pride and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the reducing you to the obedience of the Parliament; that in our Land <hi>mercy and truth may meet together, and Righteousness and Peace may kiss each other.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114598:18"/>
            <head>AN APPEAL To the <hi>Parliament, City and Kingdom:</hi> By way of ANSWER To the <hi>FƲRTHER PROGRESS</hi> in this REBELLION: To wit, The Armies last <hi>Declaration,</hi> of the 7. of <hi>December;</hi> in order to the consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating and compleating of their intended Design, To bring all men under the power and subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the wils and lusts of some in the Army, by the force and power of the Sword.</head>
            <p>ALthough it is too apparent, by what already hath been, and much more that might be said, <hi>That the proceedings of this Army, all along, ever since the beginning of this Rebellion and refusing to Disband, tend to the great dishonor of almighty God, and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the Gospel of JESUS CHRIST, and also to the subversion of the Freedom and very Being of Parliaments,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114598:19"/> in whom the <hi>Right, Liberty and property of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth and is secured;</hi> Yet it is further and more clearly evidenced and made manifest by this last <hi>Declaration,</hi> which if you please to compare with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rest of their pretences and actings everyway, together with the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> several Votes and Proceedings, and do but trace them both in their own tract, and all the affronts and strange Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, and as strangely managed, all occasioned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed backt, and but one and the same thing required and forced to pass the House by the <hi>Army,</hi> as the Free born people take the boldness to press for their upon the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said presidents, wil, I say, sufficiently declare and proclaim to the world, the usage of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and in what a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>byrinth</hi> they are now brought into, through the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, force and threatnings, continually multiplied upon them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. What is this <hi>Declaration,</hi> but, in plain terms, the prosecution of the <hi>Levellers doctrine,</hi> already Voted against as destructive to the <hi>Peace of the Kingdom,</hi> and That the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army made such a huge noise and busle to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, as if there had been such a mighty, <hi>antipathy</hi> between them really in matter of design?</p>
            <p n="2">II. Did not the <hi>Parliament</hi> Vote, <hi>That it was the duty of the Subjects of England to acquiesce in the Wisdom and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of Parliament, when the Free-born people did petition?</hi> where then is the <hi>Army</hi> that wil have what they please, and when they please, and be their own Judges, as if they were our very soveraign Lords and Masters?</p>
            <p n="3">III. What say you now to the jugling of the <hi>Army?</hi> Do you think it is of God, to play thus fast and loose in the face of a righteous God, that loves plain dealing? Hath not the whole design been carried on by craft, lyes, deceit, and all manner of filthiness and naughtiness?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Whether is it not the saddest day that ever <hi>England</hi> saw, that an <hi>Army,</hi> that would be called <hi>Saints,</hi> should ever
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114598:19"/> attempt to force a Parliament by such Menaces and Threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenings, to execute their base lusts, wils and tyrannical crueltie upon several Lords, Gentlemen, the 11. Members and others, whom the Parliament, upon the question, in the House, Voted, <hi>That, according to Law and Conscience, they could not do, nor suffer to be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. Is not the New War, they talk of, properly their own, the very Anvil they hammer all the rest of their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany on? Can you think these men do not smother many a check of conscience, when they are penning, or indeed rather drawing, as with a pensil, their own pictures? or is not this a true looking glass, wherein they may see their own faces? <hi>Even as face answereth face in a glass,</hi> so doth all their Papers set forth what manner of men they are, though with the Harlot <hi>they wipe their lips and think none see them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. What may all Rich-men, all Landed Gentlemen, Merchants, and all men of Estates, Traffique and Trading expect to see, when the Army shal thus demand money of this famous <hi>City of London,</hi> after all the kindness of this City: <hi>O the horrible ingratitude and brazen-faced impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence!</hi> you now see they begin to shew themselves in their colours, that without all colour of authority begin to threaten, and, in their own words, <hi>Joyn themselves, as equal sharers, in the Government of the Kingdom, with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in these words, say they, some seeing the Parliaments and the Armies Lenities, presume; now to that let me add thus much, that, I think, there is none but scorns any more favor or mercy from them, then he would accept at the hands of a thief he meets upon the high-way, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <hi>to give all a man has to save his life, in danger of being murdered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. What think you, is it not clear to all the world, that those men mean to destroy all Government now in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114598:20"/> force by any Law, and govern themselves? Observe how they lash the Parliament and the Government of this City, the Common Councel, and upbraid them and the House of Commons, however they dance, up and down, to usher it in with fine glosses and words, to make the best of a bad mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cover the hook with gilded shews and baites, yet do they now and then stab to the heart of this Kingdoms hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.</p>
            <p>Wel, to draw all to a <hi>conclusion,</hi> and leave it and them to the righteous God, with this prayer, <hi>That if it may stand with his glory, that he would discover to this poor Kingdom, who are the Traitors to it, who seeke to rob it of all its glory, peace and happiness;</hi> For certainly this Army cannot but sin against much Light and many checks of Conscience; the whole matter and substance of their Declaration is truly a most traiterous Comment and an undutiful and slanderous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint upon our wise and religious <hi>Senators;</hi> the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and their whole <hi>proceedings,</hi> whom I pray God <hi>bless, preserve and inable, with courage and wisdom, to carry things so, as God may not be dishonored, their own peace of Conscience wounded, this Kingdom inslaved by their negligence or cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, as knowing these light afflictions, which are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, work for us a more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> For, you may be confident, <hi>God</hi> wil ease himself of such as walk thus opposite unto him: But to return unto my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded purpose, this and all other of their <hi>Declarations</hi> affords us, in short, this plain, evident and undeniable <hi>conclusion, That the</hi> Army <hi>expects and requires that the Parliament of England must acquiesce in the Wisdom and Justice of the</hi> Army, and is really a prosecution and avowing of the <hi>Levellers do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> they so dissemblingly seemed to oppose, that they might have the better advantage to carry it on themselves: and it wil clearly appear to every indifferent Reader, by these following <hi>particulars,</hi> worth observing in their last <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114598:20"/>1. By their own admired patience, <hi>that they have quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waited upon the Parliament, for this four moneths together,</hi> as they say in the front of their <hi>Declaration;</hi> O the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous pride and intolerable insolency exercised over their masters, <hi>that by their Commissions they should only obey!</hi> Surely this is the evil effect of that foggy, cock-brain'd, blustering Hocus-pocus <hi>Peters,</hi> that common applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his prittle-prattle in the Pulpit, one of the trumpeters of Rebellion, as in his last Letter, before this Cannon came thundering about the streets, <hi>With a tantara, tantara, come away, I say, come away, there wil be a sudden storm:</hi> When our storms cease, we shal quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see <hi>Peters</hi> back-side, for he is a trout, that, yet, hath hardly lived any lived any where but in troubled waters. But to the purpose, they say they have waited; wel, I know the time when they would have waited as long upon one of the <hi>Parliament Clerks,</hi> with much more diligence and meekness, for a <hi>Commission,</hi> to be put in imployment. Yet now to the purpose; Are you not their servants? Are they not wel payd? How many hundred thousand pound hath this <hi>patient waiting</hi> cost the Kingdom? the Free-quarter they have had, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral fifty thousand pounds they had since; as for their <hi>just reward,</hi> I leave to the <hi>Righteous GOD,</hi> who, in his due time, wil pay them all, no doubt. They ought to wait, I am sure, upon the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and not thus insolently to domineer over it, and clatter their Votes about their ears, thus contrary to their Commission, their duty as English men and Christians, and double, if not treble, tyed by Protestations and Covenants; they may say what they wil, but there is neither Greek nor Hebrew, nor any ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous termes in that clause of the Covenant,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114598:21"/>
               <hi>for defending the privil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dges of Parlia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t;</hi> which all the world must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch say, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>rily consists in preserving the free Debate and Vote of the House, which cannot admit of breaking, upon any pretence whatsoever, without sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the very being of <hi>Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment:</hi> So that thus stands the case, they are now so presumptuous, that they resolve <hi>nothing shal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gn that passeth bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> what passeth also their V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, in the Councel of the Army, as the soveraign L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds and Masters of the Kingdom:</hi> They ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n estate; Do they not mean that shal serve for the <hi>Royal Assent,</hi> and so save the labor of any <hi>Personal Treatys.</hi> Or otherwise, I am sure, we have good reason to conlude, <hi>That they mean the Parliament shal measure their corn by their bushel;</hi> they must enact the sence of the Army on do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in order to the Peace of the Kingdom: but I hope our God wil be seen in the Mount to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke them by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bridle and stop them in their ful carreer; <hi>Let God arise, and let h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> enemies be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attered, and let all them that hate him flee before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By the Armies prejudging the Lord Maior, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Citizens, and the appointing the disposing of the estates in such an unusual manner, as is very much incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with the Liberty of the subject.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the contracicting of the last Vote of the House <hi>for disbanding the su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernumerary forces,</hi> and many other Votes of Parliament, and by the manner thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the money, that they, without all colour of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, demanded from the City, and the manner thereof.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the work they have appointed the Parliament to do for the present.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the time they have limited to the Parliament to do it in, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Saturday next.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s they have given to the Parliament to that purpose.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114598:21"/>8. By their menacing and threatning language, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, <hi>That if the Parliament do not satisfie them, they must either satisfie their Judgments to take some extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courses, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r that which is worse will follow,</hi> as they say.</p>
            <p n="9">9. By many, yea too many to recount, of undutiful speeches, slanders and Parliament-destroying expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nay whole sentences or what they could do with the PARLIAMENT and CITY, and all men that oppose them, if they listed; very strange Language to send to a PARLIAMENT from an ARMY of SAINTS, that should be their servants and defend them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. By their taking notice and upbraiding the <hi>House of Commons</hi> with what they do and suffer to be done, but breach of <hi>Parliament Priviledg</hi> may pass wel enough among the Croud of <hi>their Treasons,</hi> and never be seen, now adays.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Their many other petty lashes, in every page of their DECLARATION, to dishonor, and, if possible, to raise and conjure up a Spirit of <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Disobedience</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> to the <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> throughout all the Kingdom, and thousands of other particulars, which I must pass by to avoyd prolixity, that may be seen almost in every line, that it might not amount to too great a volumne.</p>
            <p n="12">12. By their refusing to obey any thing that tendeth <hi>to the setling of the Peace of the Kingdom,</hi> saying, <hi>its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Engagement, or that</hi> Sir Thomas Fairfax <hi>hath engaged himself to the contrary;</hi> It seems thats enough, if they had done no more, to bind the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> or, at least, not to oppose their <hi>Engagements and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises,</hi> so that we may see how the case stands with the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi> &amp; we may bless God, for them, that when they cannot
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114598:22"/> act for the peace of the Kingdom, that yet they wil be so faithful and courageous, as not to act against it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the threats of this Army, though they thus try all their power, skil &amp; parts to have their villany countenanced by Parliamentary Authority; I hope, through the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness and courage of our <hi>Parliament Worthies,</hi> their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons wil come in rushing with great noise, and not creeping upon us, before we are aware, by force, and not by craft, that all men may see and abhor it; that the <hi>Parliament men</hi> may have no share in losing the <hi>Kingdoms Liberties,</hi> but may enjoy the honor and comfort, what ever befals the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that they did their duty, and would not betray their trust, nor desert the ship of this <hi>Common wealth,</hi> in all those dangerous storms and tempests.</p>
            <p n="13">13. By their traiterous, reproachful and opprobrious language, they take the boldness, to the horrible disgrace and affront of the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> and to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual shame and reproach of Religion, and the unfained pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors therof, to be of all men hated &amp; unuseful to the State or Kingdom wherein they live; were it not the meer mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodness of our God, which gives me great cause to hope, <hi>He hath not quite forsaken us,</hi> only hath hid his face in his <hi>just displeasure,</hi> because of our sins, but wil return in mercy to restore this poor bleeding Kingdom to its long longed for peace and happiness, to the eternal infamy and shame of this generation of men, whose carriages we have just caus to bless God, that he hath opened the eys of so many, of late, to see, that was formerly seduced and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, judging hopefully of their good intentions, by what they had done in the time of their obedience, but now shamefully turned <hi>wolves in sheeps clothing</hi> I wil only give you their traiterous and impudent Explication, in stead of obeying the Votes of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> though the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try can wofully tel, how needful, and of necessity in order
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114598:22"/> to peace they were; If these men were for any, you shal find it in these words, in the 9. and 11. <hi>pages</hi> of this last <hi>Declaration,</hi> passing by all the rest of their stabs to the <hi>Parliaments hearts, and at Englands very being,</hi> speaking of the last distemper they, on purpose, for the ends best known to themselves, put the Army in, saith, <hi>yet now the danger is over, we see little better care of the Parliaments performance, then before, but after many days since elapsed, and some spent in professed consideration of it;</hi> the whole care of that busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness seems to be wrapt up in one bare Vote, <hi>That all super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerary forces shal be Disbanded;</hi> This being compared with what language you wil find in the 12. <hi>pag.</hi> in these words, <hi>We cannot imagine that Vote to be absolute and sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign;</hi> So that <hi>England</hi> may see, that unless, to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom, the Army may be joyned with the Parliament, nothing shal take effect, to a sudden dispatch of easing the Kingdom of its burthens; which can never be, while an Army thus domineers over our <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is, next under God, the only security, with his Majesties happy concurrence, for our very lives and estates, and any comfortable being in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="14">14. And lastly, By their invitations and cunning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuations to draw any il-affected and dissolute persons to improve this opportunity of their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to do the City all the mischief they can; I hope the <hi>Country,</hi> especially the neer neighbors of the City, hate their offer; as seeing the falseness of their <hi>pretences,</hi> and the evil and <hi>malignity</hi> of the <hi>design;</hi> surely these are no <hi>Saint-like doings,</hi> to shew so much envy and malice to those so wel-deserving from them, and wel known to all the <hi>Country,</hi> where they quarter, who, by this time, may wel enough wish they had <hi>never seen them,</hi> and see who desire and have designed a <hi>New War,</hi> if the loss of all, that were neer and dear to us, wil <hi>procure</hi> it, save only our good <hi>consciences,</hi> which they cannor plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114598:23"/> us of, since their contest; they seemed to contemn Pay much, and pretended they valued not that; so that we may now see more clearly what their design is; they must not think we are so weak to imagine it their only Design to plunder the City, that are the Contrivers or <hi>Cabbinet Counsel,</hi> though it may so fall out, by a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> as they wil cal it, to be cast in as an <hi>Overplus;</hi> but the Design is to plunder us of our Gospel, Right, Property and Liberty, and make all subject to their own wils and lusts; what is it else, think you, if they will not be guided by the Judgment of the PARLIAMENT, or if it must only consist of such Members, as, they say, have not forfeited the publick Trust? but I hope this noble and famous City wil peep so far into their designs as not to fear the plundering of this City, knowing they are too wise, if not too honest, then to think that for their advantage; For, no doubt, if they can New-mould the Parliament, fit for their turn, they shal chuse a <hi>Common Councel,</hi> to drein the City dry, to supply their wants with money: thats the way to make better use of them and their estates, for the carrying on of this intended slavery, even to the ruine of all the three Kingdoms, according to the burthen of the Song they now so much use, <hi>that they have three Kingdoms to spend;</hi> Therefore, I hope, the City wil contemn and scorn all fear of plundering, rather, then, for the prevention thereof, give any opportunity, advantage or countenance to them, while they thus watch for the <hi>ruine of the Parliament,</hi> which indeed must needs prove fatal to the <hi>Religion and Liberty of these three Kingdoms.</hi> And as for their Army of Soldiers, and most of the Officers, I know very wel, are abused, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they might, and may have their Pay, at an instant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out insisting upon such <hi>demands and conditions as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to the Freedom of Parliament,</hi> which, I am sure,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114598:23"/> they would gladly do, were they not deceived, abused and deluded by Lieut. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Privy Councel,</hi> if I do not mis-cal him; for, it may be, he only acts by <hi>Providence,</hi> and has no <hi>Commission;</hi> for, I am sure, it was often renewing in time of service, and is very long, if it be not now out of date: But that is but a punctillio, it may be he wil say, in this time of <hi>Liberty of Conscience;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I heartily wish him to deceive himself, no longer, and the <hi>Kingdom, with fancies and frothy pretences;</hi> but seriously to consider, <hi>That Rebellion is as the sin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft.</hi> And seeing he <hi>continues</hi> stil to delude the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery, and to oppress the <hi>Country,</hi> and oppose the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments easing of them,</hi> and <hi>wil suffer no remedy, but such as is wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se then the disease,</hi> as is more fully exprest in their own imperious and domineering <hi>Representation.</hi> And if you say, <hi>We are not so imperious and traiterous, as its said, for we act not at all of our selves, but with the advice of a considerable part of the Members of both Houses; who, though not the major part, yet they are those in whom the publick Trust only remains;</hi> and that I find to be the <hi>sence</hi> of most of their <hi>Declarations,</hi> and indeed is so much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted on, as if it were not only true, but a sufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to justifie and secure them from the breach both of the Law of God and the Land: as to the truth of it I desire not to say any thing, nor to dive into it, but admit it to be true, though I may hope and wish it otherwise; and, it may be, they may only speak as they would have it, being it doth not at all either justifie, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate, or lessen the treason on either part, if any such COMBINATION, COVENANTS or INGAGEMENTS were, no doubt, all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114598:24"/> all men wil grant <hi>that most apparently destructive and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent with the very Being of Parliaments, that is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and voted by the major part of the House;</hi> else might an inconsiderable number of the House plot and contrive without against the sence of the House within, to the ruin of the <hi>Kingdom and Religion also;</hi> only we may thank God that we have not only such <hi>Parliament Worthies</hi> that are courageous, but also wise, those that wil not only oppose, but are able to see and discern their designs; those are worth gold now; and I doubt not but God reckons them among his Jewels; therefore, I hope, in vain do his enemies strive, like those two <hi>Artificers,</hi> who shal draw the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillest line of policy to compass their design. Let Lie. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Privy Counsel</hi> know, that they are happy; I say, <hi>happy are they that draw the streightest line of piety, and so draw in God to be of their confederacy.</hi> But to conclude, let <hi>Italy</hi> be called the <hi>Garden of the World, for pleasure;</hi> let it be enough for <hi>England,</hi> to be called the <hi>Garden of God for Religion;</hi> the best flower in our <hi>Garden</hi> is <hi>Religion,</hi> the greatest happines of any Nation; but <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> both are the <hi>compleat happiness</hi> of a <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and how its now endangered by the Conducters of this <hi>Army:</hi> for, I know, many, if not most of the Soldiers, are averse to it, and would be more and more, did they know the depth of the design, but what it is; the famous <hi>Works, the Catechism and Confession of Faith</hi> of the <hi>Assembly of Divines,</hi> all this while smothered and opposed by that faction, may discover, as wel as the shaking of the very foundation of all <hi>Order and Government.</hi> Wel, let them and us all remember, to our comfort and their terror, that God is the best shield to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny person, the best safeguard of any <hi>Nation;</hi> if <hi>God be our enemy, nothing can secure us; if God be our friend, nothing can hurt us:</hi> Though the Army begirt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi> with the straitest siege, yet they cannot stop the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114598:24"/> from <hi>Heaven;</hi> so long as that is open there may come relief from thence, if he be our Friend, if he be in League with us; when there is no other way to escape the Army, and when as M. <hi>Peters</hi> puts them upon it, they tel us the worst, and go to execute it upon us with never so much cruelty, yet <hi>Christians</hi> may go by <hi>Heaven</hi> and escape: Let <hi>Pharaoh</hi> be behind, the <hi>Red Sea</hi> before, and the <hi>Mountains</hi> on each side, yet the <hi>Israelite</hi> can find a way; indeed Peace is a good <hi>Joseph,</hi> a good Nurse to <hi>Religion,</hi> But <hi>Religion is the Mother of Peace it self;</hi> I mean not theirs whose <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and whose <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>Faction;</hi> who with M. <hi>Peters</hi> love to fish in troubled waters, and therefore sow Division; that whilest the world is busie, playing their cruel games of War, he may have the better leasure to go away with the stakes: <hi>The Bramble thus, by renting and tearing, became King of the Trees,</hi> and so may Mr <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel;</hi> and with Champion <hi>Milo,</hi> when he thrust his hands in the cleft of an Oak, thinking to make the <hi>rent</hi> greater, if he again venter the other bout, with the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for all his craft, be caught and held also, as the Oak closed together and caught and held <hi>Milo,</hi> until he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the wild beasts, and so perished; Even so Lord put it into the hearts of our Pilots, the Parliament, that should steer the Ship of this Common-wealth, but have been too much divided and trampled under foot by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thereof, row to joyn together, that the envious men, that are thus continually sowing tares of Division in this Kingdom, may be, by their Wisdom and Courage, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate of their hopes, &amp; may reap a just reward, even their own confusion; For certainly, as the Artificer wrought his name so cunningly in the Buckler of <hi>Minerva,</hi> that not a letter could be pickt out without the dissolution of the whole frame, so cannot any of the Members of the House of Commons be pickt out or excluded otherwise, then by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114598:25"/> Vote of the major part, without the dissolution of the whole frame, and real being of that House in point of Freedom; yet Mr <hi>Cromwel</hi> proceeded to force out Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> though he since confest, to some of his friends, they had nothing against him, but that he was an active man against their party and design, and therefore must <hi>turn out:</hi> Indeed he is so compleat a Polititian, that it is as natural to him, as meat and drink, to play fast and loose with God and the Kingdom: but surely, methinks, the clear Sun-shine of the Gospel, so plentifully preacht to our English Nation, should sufficiently discover the foggy, frothy fancies, or rather devilish delusions, that Mr <hi>Cromwels</hi> extraordinary Cal or Courses are most apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opposite to the revealed Wil of God, and all the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws, now in force, in <hi>England:</hi> When the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is upon the rack, as in the Case of the Supernumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Forces, he can Disband, and he can chuse; he can draw them to the highest torment, and then give them ease by degrees: You know when a Kingdom is deadly sick, a litle ease is comfortable; but surely <hi>England</hi> thou wilt grow wiser, thou hast payd <hi>Cromwel</hi> pretty wel for thy learning. Brave <hi>English</hi> Spirits, methinks, should scorn either his <hi>canning insinuations, proud menaces, glistering new-nothings, fantastical gu-gums, or any thing else, but sudden repentance, and obedience to the revealed Wil of God and Statute Laws of the Realm.</hi> Let all true <hi>English-men</hi> say to <hi>Cromwel,</hi> as <hi>Caesar</hi> said to <hi>Phraates,</hi> that sent him a Crown, when he was up in Arms against him, but <hi>Caesar</hi> returned it back with this Answer, <hi>Facint Imperata prius,</hi> let him first return to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and then he would accept of the Crown by way of <hi>recognizance.</hi> I heartily wish they would entertain and observe these lines, as a <hi>providence,</hi> that have so much pretended to be great observers of <hi>providence,</hi> For truly I wonder they dare continue in this way of trampling upon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114598:25"/> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nay <hi>upon the revealed Wil of God and the known Laws of the Land,</hi> which, I am sure, they <hi>can never justifie, either upon any ground they have discovered, or indeed any ground they can have undiscovered;</hi> what they have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, in short, is only this, <hi>That they were raised by the Parliament, at first, to redeem the People out of slavery;</hi> and it is not yet effected; therefore they wil not Disband un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they see it done, nay until they say it is done, and <hi>That,</hi> I wil tel them, they have already given us ground enough to say, <hi>wil never be,</hi> until it be undone: But this, I am sure, the Parliament never said in any of their <hi>Declarations,</hi> that they should be Judges, when the people were in, &amp; when they were out of slavery. May not any number of men whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever quickly have as good call as their pretences are? I think I may wel enough conclude they never wil establish Peace, it being something against their profit, and that which wil spoil their trade, but admit their intentions good, whats this to their Gal either from God or men, to undertake that only proper to <hi>Parliaments.</hi> Besides, I am sure Lieut. Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> had no Warrant, either from God or man, to send <hi>Joyce</hi> for the King at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> and then declare to all the world, he never knew of, nor had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hand in it. I wil give you their principal Arguments that in any discourse I can hear from them, which I have not already so clearly exprest: They say first, their <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was to this purpose, <hi>To reform all things amiss in the Kingdom, and set the free People at Liberty out of all manner of Bondage; and to this purpose they were raised.</hi> For answer hereunto, I am sure they have granted it, that if they had undertook to have fought in these Wars, as they have done, without Authority from <hi>Parliament,</hi> that they had been but Traitors, and that they could not prosecute the War, but by the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Instructions. And I know the time when Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and all the rest of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114598:26"/> would not undertake to do any thing, though it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so much tended to the advantage of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some clause in some Order or Ordinance of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to bear them out. Can any men be so unrational to to imagine, or any so impudent to affirm, That the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> should ever give any other <hi>Commission</hi> then what ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth them to the <hi>obedience</hi> of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever alteration, orders and direction, from time to time; they shal give, which is the very tenor of their <hi>Commissions,</hi> and there can be no doubt but they might as wel have raised themselves without authority from <hi>Parliament,</hi> as for them now to continue in a Body, when both Houses by <hi>Ordinance</hi> hath commanded their <hi>Disbanding;</hi> And they might as wel and upon the same ground have proceeded, acted and done all these things, which of late they have done, when they were first raised as now: That now after all the blood and treasure they have spilt and spent, to question the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> nay the very <hi>Parliament,</hi> upon whose authority they have only acted, and without which, I presume they would have thought, as no doubt it is, even plain murder and robbery; and for them to tel the Kingdom of making a free Parliament, is as strange a cheat as the rest of their proceedings, that they should act all this while, while there was any money or plunder to be got, or until they were just to be disbanded, which more then intimates, that if the Army had been Voted, in stead of Disbanding, to have been establisht for seven years, with good pay, the <hi>Parliament</hi> had been free enough to have done that; as it was ever since they were raised until that time, and if the City of <hi>London</hi> had been but as noble and generous to continue dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bursing the old plentiful loans of money, they had been the gallant City stil, but if they joyn with <hi>Parliament</hi> to ease the Kingdom of an Army, then they are clearly for a New War; for either they must continue undisbanded, or it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114598:26"/> seems there must be a new War, if they can procure it, all the Members must turn out, but who wil Vote for the <hi>Armies continuance,</hi> and then <hi>we have a free Parliament</hi> say they; for many of their Commanders say <hi>they have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-slipt their opportunity, that when they marched through the City they did not make the House of Commons for their turn, for now they could not do it without too much noise in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; yet they doubted it would never be until it was done:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, all may now see there was nothing but jugling in all the pretended divisions in the Army, and that they can be out and in as often as they please, when it is advantageous for their Design. May not one conclude, That their design cannot be compleated before they come to quarter in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> and deface that glorious and excellent Government, the wonder of the world; and the principal defenders of the true Religion and Fundamental Laws of the Land, and of the Liberty and Property of the Subject, that they may make sure work with al the Kingdom, &amp; finish the work by forcing out the Members, and chopping and changing them until they wil act the sence of the Army; Let them speak the truth, if this be not their Design, in attempting to come to <hi>London,</hi> which inevitably must destroy thousands of Tradesmen wholy, and crack the whole frame of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City by an universal decay of Trade and ruine of the whole Nation, under <hi>pretences,</hi> which being inquired into wil appear to be meer bubles and vanishing shadow, that hath nothing but deceit and couzenage in them; Though whatsoever Vote passes to their benefit to bring them in money is very soveraign, and that, I wil warrant you, they wil act upon to the ful; so that, I think, upon the matter, it is as clear as the Sun, that the quarrel between the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and the <hi>Army</hi> is in whom the Supream power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists: For now adays there is hardly any <hi>Command</hi> goes from the <hi>Parliament</hi> but the <hi>Army</hi> expects it should be taken for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114598:27"/> a great favor, if they obey it, and there is not any <hi>obedience</hi> to be given, until it receive the <hi>concurrence</hi> of the <hi>General Councel.</hi> Do they not think they are fine youths, that the Votes of the House cannot be obeyed except they send a Committee down to intreat for it, or to treat and debate it over again, as they are fain to do about Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>banding the <hi>Supernumeraries,</hi> and what other Votes then also past the House; The <hi>Parliament</hi> must give the <hi>Army</hi> content, and not the <hi>Army</hi> the <hi>Parliament;</hi> It seems the <hi>Parliament</hi> must walk up to their principles, and not the <hi>Army</hi> come down to theirs: But surely all the world wil now see this <hi>Treason and intended ruin of the Kingdom,</hi> and not any longer be deceived and deluded with a rebellious, proud and discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faction in the Army, that, to have their wils, care not to ruin a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> nay <hi>three Kingdoms</hi> at a clap. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was to be done by them, or was set forth in any <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> I am sure, did never make them Judges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor of the <hi>Case of the Kingdom;</hi> and can they be so impudent to plead any extraordinary Cal or Direction from God for them to take upon them to judg the very House it self and their Members: but I have said so much that I hope I need not say any more, to clear their practices to be without any shadow, either of godliness or common Christianity; and ever heartily wish that they may observe it for a providence that are so much pretenders to observe <hi>providences;</hi> and even lay aside every sin that hath so easily beset them, and seek <hi>the Lord mightily, while he may be found,</hi> least he shew, by some imminent token to the Kingdom, his most high displeasure against them, and even suffer them to be wholy swallowed up and devoured with those <hi>strange delusions,</hi> that so many of the Army are so shamefully infected with, at this day, very dangerously back sliding from the revealed Wil and Truth of God. So that upon the whole matter we must needs make this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114598:27"/>
               <hi>construction, that the Officers of the Army surely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the infinite disproportion between their Worships now in the head of an Army, and their own several conditions and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their ordinary Callings, being once out of their Military imployment,</hi> who, being <hi>conscious</hi> of their own guilt, dare not trust the <hi>Justice of the Law</hi> or <hi>Goodness of the Parliament</hi> but chuse rather to preserve themselvs by the power of an Army, though it endangers the <hi>impoverishing and utter ruin of this poor Kingdom:</hi> and it certainly is a most high degree of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> that put them upon those courses: They could not, with <hi>Haman,</hi> indure a <hi>Mordecai</hi> in the House of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> for notwithstanding all their Victories in the field, if they had it not in the Parliament also, that so thereby they might lord it over all men as the Conquerors, it would not be lasting. To that purpose they had got the length of the peoples feet, as we used to say, and whatsoever was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss, they pretended to be very sensible of, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, and so takes the only course to send us head long to destruction, in stead of falling upon them, or that, or there, where truly the fault lies, they fel upon breaking down the very banks, to let in the whole flood or ocean of <hi>destruction</hi> to unavoydably drown us, which the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath much ado to <hi>prevent.</hi> Alas the people knew <hi>things</hi> were amiss, but upon whom, or where the fault lay, they knew not; but all willing to beleeve, and they as undutifully, as falsly and maliciously charged it upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Committees and Officers, whose miscarriages, that they <hi>complain</hi> of, <hi>principally</hi> lay where and upon whom they protect, as particularly, the <hi>Money Merchants:</hi> speak truly, are not they, their <hi>friends and faction</hi> the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and devourers of the <hi>Kingdoms treasure;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause others should not bring them to <hi>account,</hi> and <hi>prevent</hi> any more <hi>opportunities</hi> or <hi>advantages,</hi> for them to hord up more, have done all this: would not the <hi>Disbanding</hi> of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114598:28"/>
               <hi>Army</hi> remove all or most of the burthens that lie upon the <hi>Kingdom?</hi> and must not the continuance of it bring such debts as are impossible to be payd with such havock and every where destruction to the provision of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that its like to bring a Famine; besides the Soldiers domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over every man in his own house, that we are upon the matter, no beter then slaves; though we could not see this before, we see it now; bisides they know Religion and Peace are not to be establisht by men of War; when the Church had rest, in the <hi>Acts,</hi> then it multiplied. <hi>David,</hi> a man of War, must not build the Temple, but <hi>Solomon</hi> a King of Peace. You know, in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, they were forced to stand with a trowel in one hand, and a sword in the other, Religion went but slowly forward; and the reason was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the earth must stand stil, on purpose, that it may sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us to run the way of Gods Commandments. And as <hi>Antigonus</hi> told the <hi>Sophister</hi> he came out of seasons when he presented a Treatise of Justice to him, that was at that very time besieging a City: and as its said, <hi>Soldiers cannot possibly hear the voyce of the Laws for tho noise of the Drums;</hi> and that, I beleeve, did make Mr <hi>Peters</hi> so inveigh against the Lawyers going up and down to <hi>Westminster,</hi> in his last Pamphlet: and indeed if the Army may come to quarter in the City, and M. <hi>Peters</hi> advice followed, few wil have any estates to go to Law for; but because the Laws of God and the Land and the voyce of the Gospel cannot be heard, let us pray for the peace of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> but if no peace, then let the Parliament and the City know, that though this generation of men should resolve to have their wils, though with the loss of a good <hi>Conscience,</hi> and with the <hi>Scythians,</hi> that scoffingly answered <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he, hoping they would have answered of himself, asked them who they were most afraid of; said, they were most afraid least Heaven should fal upon them, meaning they feared
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114598:28"/> no enemy. Let not us therefore indeed fear any thing, but this only, least God should be our Enemy; For as <hi>Noah,</hi> when the deluge of waters had defaced the great Book of Nature, had a Copy of every kind of Creature in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Liberary of the Ark, out of which all were reprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the world; so we, that have God, have the Original Copy of all blessings, out of which, if by this generation of monsters, I mean those that have put the Army into this distemper, all were perished, all might easily be restored again, for God is the best store house a people can have; <hi>The Name of the Lord is a strong tower, and the righteous flie unto it and are safe.</hi> Remember how lovingly the City late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their <hi>Petition</hi> offered to take them by the hand to help them out of this labyrinth. I am sorry to see the Army should make so ill use thereof, and with the Dog <hi>to return to the vomit again,</hi> and shake hands with the Levellers. Wel, let the City take notice, its not good walking any more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very brink of danger; let them take heed of tempting of God, they owned some, if not too in any, of their faults, and set that upon their own score they were innocent in, and I am sure offered to pay the Armies debts, though but scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For a final close, if with the fool, <hi>they wil say in their hearts there is no God,</hi> and so go on to ruin the Parliament and City, in their own strength and wisdom, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, lest as <hi>Philip</hi> branded that Soldier that begged the lands of one that had entertained him kindly, with <hi>ingratus hospes</hi> on his forehead, so that God brand not them with this ignominious note of an unthankful people, an ungrateful Army: I think their late disobedience wil be as litle honor to the Army, as for <hi>Pilates</hi> name to be mentioned in the Creed; Religion cannot be practiced without reward, and wil not be contemned without danger. I wil conclude with <hi>Artabazu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> who complained, when <hi>Syrus</hi> had given him a cup of gold, and <hi>Chrysantes</hi> but a kiss, in token
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114598:29"/> of special favor, that the cup of gold was not so good as the kiss he gave <hi>Chrysantes:</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> was wont to say, That he had rather have a Kings countenance then his coyn: I am sure I had rather have a good look from God, then all the glistering prosperity this wo ld affords, or this Army doth enjoy: A Christian thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self richer, when he is able to say God is mine, then if he had a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Mynes of Gold: and then, though much amazed at the Armies proceedings and successes in all their treasonable undertakings and God-loathing-dissemblings; yet when I remember wherefore <hi>the way of the wicked prosper, and wherefore they are happy that deal treacherously with the Lord,</hi> then <hi>in the multitude of my thoughts his comforts delight my soul:</hi> And so casting the anchor of my faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his never-failing Word of Truth, I fully acquiesce and conclude, <hi>Verily there is a reward with the righteous, verily there is a God that uprightly judgeth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SOme change of words there is in this Book, for want of the Authors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany at the printing, which wil require thy care in reading, that a good interpretation may be put upon that which is easily discerned not to be the Authors meaning; The greatest mistake you shal find in the sixth page, and very little elswhere. Tel me if it be not a strange cheat to the Kingdom, that the Army should act all this while, as long as plunder and pay was plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and yet after al this, and not before they were Voted to disband, should then fal upon that very Parliament, &amp; then shamefully tear it in pieces, limb by limb, and yet tel us they are making us a free Parliament, but that all the world may see they only aim at the inslaving of this Kingdom, and to be a perpetual Army, remember the particulars in this Book, &amp; that the Parliament was never molested before but free, as they have acknowledged, and especially confirmed by their actions: for, if it were not a free Parliament, they ought not to have acted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Commission and other several Orders and Ordinances; so that now all the world must needs say they strive for a New War, &amp; have done nothing else, ever since they were Voted to be Disbanded, but promote it sometimes rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling against the Parliament, sometimes forcing them, sometimes inveighing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Ministers, sometimes against the Scot, and every day studying new quarrels, how to bring about more imployment for themselves, that they might prevent their own disbanding. I wonder they dare, in the face of the Son of God, contnue in a body to eat and drink the sweat of other mens brows and labors to the hazarding a sudden Famine by their access and wantoness, and indeed even the perishing of many poor families in the Country <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> above all I am sorry to see Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> thus drawn in to continue among the croud, for all the several steps of their proceedings, ever since their advance to Saint <hi>Albius,</hi> have been the promoting a New War; you shal see if they do not procure one at last, without God, in his great mercy, to this poor Kingdom, prevent it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>